Preliminary Guide to the Communication Department, records, 1917-2002 RG0090
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
School of Media and Public Affairs records
1917-2002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0090
3 Linear Feet
Materials in this collection include departmental files and blueprints for Building YY (814 20th Street, NW). The departmental files include brochures, memorandums, newsletters, flyers, invitations, announcements, photographs, programs, press releases, and posters. They range in date from 1917 to 2002. The materials concern radio programs, television programs, courses, College of General Studies, the Department of Speech and Drama, "GW Underground", WRGW history, drama productions, biographic information, forensics workshops for teachers, speech pathology, audiology, graduate studies, plans for a GW - WETA Communications Center, GW Television Station, courses airing on television, seminars, teleconferences, videoconferences, GW television station services, and High School Discussion Conferences.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The majority of the records were transferred to the University Archives by the Chair of the Department of Communication.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Department of Communication at The George Washington University began in 1987, and offered an undergraduate degree in radio and television communications. Before that it was part of the Department of Communication and Theatre, which offered undergraduate degrees in speech communication, theater, and radio-television. Before 1983, it was known as the Department of Speech and Drama.
Now a part of the School of Media and Public Affairs (SMPA), the curriculum focuses on the media and the many important relationships among media, culture, and the various institution of public life, government, education, corporations, and associations.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include departmental files and blueprints for Building YY (814 20th Street, NW). They range in date from 1917-2002. The blueprints were transferred to the University Archives by the Chair of the Department of Communication, while the departmental files were formerly vertical files in the Special Collections Research Center.
Formerly RG9.9
Collection Organization
Organized in four series: Departmental files, Blueprints, Associate Dean C. Sterling Records on Development of Communication at George Washington University, and reel to reels.
Bib#
8127774
Washington (D.C.); Photographs; Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Journalism; Communication in politics; Digital media; Blueprints (reprographic copies); George Washington University. Dept. of Communication; George Washington University; George Washington University. School of Media and Public Affairs
- Departmental files, 1917-2002; RG0090 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains brochures, memorandums, newsletters, flyers, invitations, announcements, photographs, programs, press releases, and posters. They range in date from 1917 to 2002. The materials concern radio programs, television programs, WTOP, WCFM, WMAL, WRC, WCFM, courses, College of General Studies, the Department of Speech and Drama, "GW Underground", WRGW history, drama productions, biographic information, forensics workshops for teachers, speech pathology, audiology, graduate studies, plans for a GW - WETA Communications Center, GW Television Station, courses airing on television, seminars, teleconferences, videoconferences, GW television station services, and High School Discussion Conferences.
  Formerly vertical files
  - High School Discussion Conferences, 12/08/1964-11/13/1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Radio and Television Courses, 09/13/1963-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Radio Station (WRGW), 1980 ca.-06/2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Speech and Drama Department, 10/26/1974-06/27/1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Speech and Drama Department - Drama Announcements, 07/14/1965-06/10/1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Speech and Drama Department - Drama Productions of Agamemnon, Noah and Our American Cousin with bio of Edward Mangum, Assistant Professor of Speech and Drama, 1950, 03/13/1948-06/09/1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Speech and Drama Department - Drama Programs, 1909-1949, 1917-04/24/1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Speech and Drama Department - Drama Programs, 1950-1972, 04/21/1949-12/1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Speech and Drama Department Drama Programs, 1973-1981, 02/04/1974-04/11/1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Speech and Drama Department - Drama Programs Homecoming Productions, 1955-1968, 11/03/1955-10/31/1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Speech and Drama Department - Forensics, 06/1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Speech and Drama Department - Speech Pathology and Audiology, 10/1967-1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Television Station, 09/22/1982-1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Television Station WETA-TV Project, 1992, 05/1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Blueprints, 1984-1985; RG0090 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  Blueprints for Building YY (814 20th Street) - Radio and T.V. Department, 1984-1985.
  Formerly Acc#64
  This series has a paper container list in the reading room, please ask staff for assistance.
- Associate Dean C. Sterling Records on Development of Communication at George Washington Universityn, 1980-1996; RG0090 Series 3; 0.50 Linear Feet
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials from Associate Dean Christopher Sterling pertaining to the creation of the School of Media and Public Affairs, dating from 1980-1996.
  - Growth of Electronic Media Major, 1982-1985; RG0090 Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Shift From Deptartment of Speech and Drama to Communication, 1983; RG0090 Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Department of Communication, 1980; RG0090 Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Formation of NCCS, 1989-1993; RG0090 Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Developing NCCS Peer Review Process, 1991-1996; RG0090 Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence about NCCS Formation and a New Building, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Briefing for Donald R. Lehman, August 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Information about the status of the new SMPA Building.
  - Media and Public Affairs Building - Concept Program and Schematic Design Program Summary, May 1997-September 1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Media and Public Affairs Building - drawings, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence about MPA Building, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Reel to reel lectures, 1960-1969; RG0090 Series 4
  The reel to reels in this collection are a majority recordings of "Lectures in Miniature." Lectures in Miniature was a joint program between GW and WMAL Radio and produced by Lillian Brown, director of the then-department of Radio and Television. The lectures were five minute programs with one member of the GW Faculty in their area of expertise.
  Accession 2012.062
  - Lectures and presentations recordings, 1963-1966; RG0090 Series 4 Subseries 1
    - GWU hospital groundbreaking dedication ceremony, 1966 May 11 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      The groundbreaking dedication ceremony for the hospital. Speakers: Dr. John Parks, Mr. Ellison, Mrs. Myer, Hon. John McCormack, Speaker of the US House of Representatives.
    - GWU - A changing campus, 1966 March 30 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Clark, Joseph S. - "Congress: A Sapless Branch", 1965 March 10 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Address by Senator Joseph S. Clark (Democrat, Pennsylvania) - GW Public Affairs series, Lisner Auditorium at 8pm on March 10, 1965. A question and answer session answering such questions as should there be four year terms for Congressmen and other questions about the two party system.
    - Clarkson, Natasha - Contemporary Russian literature (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Discussion of Russian Poetry and literature. Also, radio time taped with Dick Van Dyke.
    - Hunt, Dr. Thelma - "Mental health in the modern world", 1963 June (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Discusses the nature of mental health, its origins and problems.
    - Huseman, Frank G. - "Trends in visual communication" (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Discusses communications thorugh sight.
    - Vetter, Charles - "America's challenger to communicate" (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Guest lecture
  - "Lectures in Miniature" recordings, RG0090 Series 4 Subseries 2
    Biographical / Historical
    The Lectures in Miniature series was a joint program between News and Public Affairs Department of WMAL Radio and GW. Its purpose was to "bring to the radio listener educational information in a consise, palpable form." The series featured a weekly lecture from a University professor with a three to five minute broadcast on a subject of their choosing. The five daily lectures could be interrelated or independent.
    - Campbell, Robert - "Revolution in Geography" (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Discusses geography's interdisciplinary role in education.
    - Kirkbride, Dean Virginia - "Learning outside the classroom in the academic community" (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Kirsch, Arthur - "Study of American drinking" (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Kramer, Dean Robert - "administrators and the courts", 1962 October (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Latimer, Dr. John F. - "Excerpts from a Greek poet" (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Leggette, Dr. Poe - "Five essentials of good speech", 1962 June (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Dr. Poe Leggette was Depew professor of Speech at GW.
    - Kullback, Solomon - "Introduction to the information theory" (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Levitan, Dr. S - "Federal aid to depressed areas" (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Linton, Dean Calvin D. - "The Greek anthology" (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Dean Calvin D. Linton was the dean of the Columbian College of Arts and Sciences.
    - Mason, Dean Martin A. - "The engineer...his obligations", 1962 June (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Dr. Mason was the dean of the school of engineering.
    - Mazzeo, Dr. Guido E. - "The neoclassical romantic periods in Spanish literature" (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - McIntyre, Margaret - "Creativity in young children" (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Ojalvo, Morris S. - "Engineering and your utilities" (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Olkhovsky, George - "The communist party and the Soviet Intellectuals" (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Osanka, Franklin Mark - "Modern guerrilla warfare", 1962 September (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Page, Dr. Harry - "Ethics in business" (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Phillips, Dr. E.L. - "Psychology testing", 1963 January (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Pierpoint, Dr. Howard - "History of heart surgery", 1963 February (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Rashid, Dr. Martha - "The gifted child" (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Reesing Jr., Dr. John - "Milton's development in human sympathy" (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Riggs, Robert - "A French woman's view of the 1840s" (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Robertson, James - "A discussion of the Civil War" (Box 3, Folder 16)
      James Robertson, head of the Civil War Centennial Commission, and instructor at GWU on the Civil War. Discussion of outbreak of the Civil War, conspicuous leaders of the 1860s, war of the plain folk, downfall of the confederacy and lessons of the civil war.
    - Ruddley, John - "Art and society", 1962 October (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Ruth, Joseph Y. - "Selecting a college" (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Joseph Ruth was the director of admissions
    - Sadusk, Dr. Joseph - "Continuing care program - hospital", 1962 October (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Schilling, Dr. Charles - "Scientific communications problems" (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Schlesinger, Dr. Lawrence - "The things our inner voice tells us" (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Seidman, Aaron - "The old testament", 1963 June (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Sizoo, Dr. Joseph - "Christmas in today's world", 1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Skelton, Dr. Martin - "British national health service" (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Smith, Dean Herbert - "Engineering and applied science" (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Snodgrass, Jeanne - "Growth and development needs for life" (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Steiner, George - "Five vignettes on Bach, Debussy, Haydn, Purcell, Stravinsky", 1962 July (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Stone, Dr. Helen - "Readiness for college" (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Telford, Dr. Ira - "Genetics" (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Thoenelt, Dr. Klaus - "German and American Faust" (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Dr. Klaus Thoenelt of the GW Department of German languages and literatures discusses Goethe's Faust - its parallels with American literature and the ultimate redeption of the legendary character.
    - Towne, Mildred - "Modern everyday textiles" (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Tracey, Stan - "Youth needs to know", 1962 November (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Walk, Dr. Richard - "The study of visual depth perception" (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Walther, Dr. Carl H. - "Education of tomorrow's engineers" (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Weihofen, Henry - "Mental incompetency and the law" (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Yeide, Harry. E. Jr - "History and significance" (Box 4, Folder 9)